Guide to the Washington Office on Africa Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Washington Office on Africa Records
1966-1994
RG 105
Yale University Divinity School Library
30
(66 boxes)
Publications, correspondence, reports, statements, and collected material document the work of the Washington Office on Africa and the issues addressed by its work. The Washington Office on Africa was founded in 1972 to support the movement for freedom from white-minority rule in southern Africa. Its activities have included the monitoring of Congressional legislation and executive policies and actions, as well as the publication of action alerts and other documentation designed to advance progressive legislation and policy on southern Africa. Supported by church bodies and unions, the WOA has worked in partnership with colleagues in Africa, the Africa advocacy community in the United States, and grassroots organizations concerned with various aspects of African affairs.
Washington Office on Africa
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Washington Office on Africa.
Biographical / Historical
The Washington Office on Africa was founded in September 1972 as a non-profit, church and labor union-supported organization to work with Congress on southern Africa legislation. WOA began by mobilizing around the issue of repealing the Byrd Amendment passed in 1971, which allowed the United States to break sanctions that had been imposed on Rhodesia. Issues that were the focus of WOA activities included:
- legislation related to U. S. covert intervention in Angola
- passage of 1977 legislation making the U. S. comply with international trade sanctions against Rhodesia (now independent Zimbabwe
- a 1978 cut-off of U. S. Export-Import credits to South Africa
- passage of legislation restricting U. S. support for IMF loans to South Africa
- passage in the House of Representatives of the 1985 anti-apartheid act
- prevention of shipments of nuclear materials and technology to South Africa
- passage of state, local, and institutional divestment of over five billion dollars in public and institutional funds from South Africa
- U.S. policy toward conflict in Namibia, Zimbabwe, and Mozambique
-comprehensive sanctions against South Africa
WOA was established at the direct initiative of American churches, who felt the necessity for a Washington-based organization able to provide the religious community with up-to-date infomration on U. S. policy in Southern Africa. Through the years, the office broadened its constituency to include trade unions, student groups, and other grassroots organizations. Sponsors of the Washington Office on Africa included: African Methodist Episcopal Church, Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union, The American Committee on Africa, Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), Church of the Brethren, Episcopal Church, Evangelical Lutheran Church in America, Missionaries of Africa, Presbyterian Church (USA), Progressive National Baptist Convention, The Reformed Church of America, Sacred Heart Fathers, Society for African Missions, United Automobile, Aerospace and Agricultural Implement Workers of America, United church of Christ, United Methodist Church, United Steelworkers of America.
The Washington Office on Africa Educational Fund (WOAEF) was established as the educational division of the Washington Office on Africa. Its goals were to provide education for action on southern Africa issues through the production and distribution of written and audio-visual resources. WOAEF also served as a research center for educators, legislators, political activists, students, and others interested in southern Africa affairs.
Executive Directors of the WOA included Ted Lockwood (1972-1980), Jean Sindab (1980-1986), Damu Smith (1986-1988), and Aubrey McCutcheon (1988-199?). The WOA weathered a financial crisis in 1988.
Scope and Contents
I. Organization and Policy Records
II. Correspondence and Staff Records
III. Fundraising and Financial Records
IV. WOA Programs
V. WOA Publications
VI. Resource Files - By Name of Organization
VII. Resource Files - By State/Region
VIII. Resource Files - By Topic
When these records were received, some printed materials were removed and placed with the Sterling Memorial Library Manuscripts and Archives South African apartheid collection, MS 1500. The material remaining in this record group relates more to the actual operations of WOA, its publications and activities, and its interactions with other organizations. The topical resources in this record group were collected to support and direct the lobbying and advocacy activities of the WOA.
Series I, Organization and Policy Records, includes minutes and reports of the boards and committees of the WOA and the Washington Office on Africa Educational Fund. These materials provide a succinct overview of the activities of the organization. Series II, Correspondence and Staff Records, is quite small and primarily relates to internal office operations; the majority of letters and memoranda of the WOA Directors and staff are integrated into later series. Series III, Fundraising and Financial Records, is divided into three sub-series: Summary Records, Chronological Sequence of Records, Correspondence with Notable Funding Agencies.
Series IV, WOA Programs, is the core of this record group. It includes an alphabetical listing of programs and proposals sponsored or co-sponsored by WOA, and a chronological arrangement of material related to the lobbying and monitoring activities of the WOA. Material in this series provides valuable documentation about the issues that were of concern to WOA as well as about the lobbying process and the WOA's interaction with related organizations.
Series V, WOA Publications, includes publications with distinctive titles. Many other WOA statements, papers, and press releases are integrated with the program material of Series IV. The major serial publications of WOA were Action Alert, and Washington Notes on Africa. Other publications included "Information Packets." brochures and printed leaflets, and "Fact Sheets."
Series VI, Resources by Organization, include correspondence between the WOA and related organizations as well as printed material documenting the work of those organizations. This alphabetically arranged list includes a broad cross section of U.S. and African organizations concerned with issues in Southern Africa. Series VII, Resources by State/Region, documents WOA's interaction with and monitoring of Southern Africa-related events and programs throughout the United States. Series VIII, Resources by Topic, is divided into three sub-series: Country Files, Economic and Foreign Policy Issues (U.S. interaction with Southern Africa), and Miscellaneous. The Country Files are strongest in documentation of events and issues in Angola, Namibia, South Africa, and Zimbabwe. Of particular note are materials related to church activities and reactions in these countries. Economic and Foreign Policy issues documented in Series VIII include the arms trade, boycotts, divestment and investment in South Africa, espionage, international economic and trade issues, and sanctions. This material should be consulted in conjunction with the WOA program materials of Series IV, which document WOA positions and actions on the various issues.
Some complementary records related to WOA activities have been digitized by the Michigan State African Activist Archive and the University of Pennsylvania's African Studies Center.
Arrangement
I. Organization and Policy Records
II. Correspondence and Staff Records
III. Fundraising and Financial Records
IV. WOA Programs
V. WOA Publications
VI. Resource Files - By Name of Organization
VII. Resource Files - By State/Region
VIII. Resource Files - By Topic
Anti-apartheid movements -- United States; Apartheid -- South Africa; Church and state -- United States; Disinvestment; Lobbying -- Law and legislation -- United States; Angola -- Politics and government; Mozambique -- Politics and government; Namibia -- Politics and government; South Africa -- Politics and government -- 1978-1989; United States -- Foreign relations -- South Africa; Zimbabwe -- Politics and government; Washington Office on Africa
- Organization and Policy Records, Series I
  - Washington Office on Africa
    - Minutes of Steering Committee, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Policy guidelines, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bylaws, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Minutes of Board of Directors; Report of Search Committee for new Executive Director, 1978, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Minutes, reports re. tenth anniversary of WOA, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Minutes of Board of Directors; WOA self-evaluation documents, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Minutes, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Annual report, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Minutes, meeting packet, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Annual report, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Board and Executive Committee of Board agenda, meeting packet, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Corres. re. financial crisis, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Meeting packet, 1989 Jan (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Minutes, 1989 Nov (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Minutes, agendas, reports, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Minutes, reports, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Washington Office on Africa Educational Fund
    - Bylaws, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Minutes of Board of Directors, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Minutes of Board of Directors, 1982-1983, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Advisory Group to WOAEF - minutes, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Agenda, reports, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Minutes and meeting packet, 1985 Jun (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Minutes, reports, 1985 Dec (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Agenda, reports, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Program activity reports; report of Religious Outreach Coordinator, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Program activity reports, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Agendas, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Agenda, reports, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Correspondence and Staff Records, Series II
  - Executive Director Files
    - Ted Lockwood (1972-1980)
      - Correspondence, 1973-1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Notes, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Writings, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Writings; incl. outline and drafts for "South Africa: Kairos and Krisis", 1982, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Jean Sindab (1980-1986)
      - Correspondence, writings, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Damu Smith (1986-1988)
      - Biographical info; correspondence, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Delegation to Cuba, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Aubrey McCutcheon (1989-199?)
      - Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Internal office communications
    - Administrative forms, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Job descriptions; staff info., 1983-1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Memos, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Re. tax matters, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Staff meeting notes, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Memos, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Memos, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Memos re. campaign, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Assistant Director's notes, drafts, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Assistant Director's notes, drafts, corres., 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Memos, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Associate Director's corres; memos, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence with others
    Scope and Contents
    For correspondence with related organizations, see Series VI
    - Re. intern program, 1982-1989 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
    - With prisoners in U.S., 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Fundraising and Financial Records, Series III
  - Summary records
    - Financial statements, 1973, 1975 1984-1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Chronological sequence
    - Fundraising correspondence and records, 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 2-8)
    - Proposal for funding 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Fundraising correspondence and records, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Fundraising correspondence and records; funding proposal, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Proposal for funding, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
    - Fundraising correspondence and records, 1982-1984 (Box 4, Folder 14-16)
    - Proposal for funding, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 17-19)
    - Fundraising correspondence and records, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 20-23)
    - Fundraising correspondence and records; preparation for audit, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Fundraising correspondence and records, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Mailing lists, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 26-28)
  - Notable funding agencies
    - National Community Funds, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - New World Foundation, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Ottinger Foundation, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Skaggs Foundation, 1984-1988 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - United Nations Centre Against Apartheid, 1982-1987 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - United Nations Council for Namibia, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - United Support of Artists for Africa, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - World Council of Churches Programme to Combat Racism, 1984-1987 (Box 5, Folder 36)
- WOA Programs, Series IV
  - Programs, proposals sponsored or co-sponsored by WOA
    - Africa Peace Tour (Africa Peace Committee), 1986-1989 (Box 6, Folder 1-9)
    - Africa Peace Tour, 1990-1992, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 10-12)
    - "Amandla" - audio-visual presentation re. apartheid in S. Africa, 1983-1984 (Box 8, Folder 13-15)
    - Angola audio-visual project, 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Boycott campaigns (cultural, sports) - See also Series VIII, Resource File - Economic and Foreign Policy issues - Boycotts (Box 8, Folder 17-19)
    - Campaign to End US/SA Nuclear Collaboration proposal, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Demonstrations/ rallies: re. US intervention in Angola / Soweto massacre, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Demonstrations/ rallies: re. visit of Ian Smith, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Demonstrations/ rallies: re. visit of Jonas Savimbi, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Demonstrations/ rallies: miscellaneous, 1985-1990 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - "Feminization of Poverty: A Global Problem" proposal, ca. 1985 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - "A Free South Africa Movement Project" proposal, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - "The Harare Declaration Action Campaign" proposal, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Hotline, 1990, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - IMPACT Peace Network / Team, 1981-1985 (Box 9, Folder 29-31)
    - Mandela tributes, petition, 1982-1983 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Martin Luther King Symposium, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Martin Luther King Symposium, 1988-1989 (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Miscellaneous events, presentations by staff, 1984-1992 (Box 10, Folder 35-39)
    - Namibia: Delegation of Namibian Church Leaders, 1986 Dec (Box 10, Folder 40)
    - Namibia Briefing, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 41)
    - Namibia: Free Namibia campaign, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 42)
    - Namibia Hearings (May 2-4, 1988) - sponsored by WCC PCR; coordinated by WOA - Correspondence, memos, 1988 Jan-Mar (Box 10, Folder 43)
    - Namibia Hearings - Correspondence, memos, 1988 Apr- May (Box 10, Folder 44)
    - Namibia Hearings - Schedules, logistics, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 45)
    - Namibia Hearings - Press releases, publicity, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 46)
    - Namibia Hearings - Background material, program, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 47)
    - Namibia Hearings - Statements, testimony, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 48)
    - Namibia workshops, hearings, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 49)
    - Ndilimani tour: Cultural Ensemble of the South West Africa Peoples' Organization (SWAPO) of Namibia, 1986-1987 (Box 11, Folder 50-51)
    - Nuclear Collaboration and Freeze Campaign, 1983-1984 (Box 11, Folder 52)
    - Peace in Angola - Emergency Grassroots Education Project, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 53)
    - Religious Legislative Advocacy and Information Network on Southern Africa, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 54)
    - Southern Africa Hunger and Development Educaton Project proposal, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 55)
    - Southern Africa Working Group (SAWG), 1981-1991 (Box 12, Folder 57-59)
    - Southern African Women in Crisis: A Grassroots Support Guide - proposal, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 60)
    - Spotlight on Apartheid in Southern Africa proposal, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 61)
    - Spotlight on Southern Africa proposal, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 62)
    - Stopping the South African War Machine proposal, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 63)
    - Visitors to U.S., 1969-1987 (Box 12, Folder 64-65)
    - Work with students - requests for information and literature, 1983-1986 (Box 13, Folder 66-67)
    - Work with students - protests, organizing activities, 1983-1986 (Box 13, Folder 68)
    - Work with students - student activist questionnaire, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 69)
  - Lobbying/monitoring activities
    - WOA precursors
      - South Africa Sugar Quota - American Committee on Africa correspondence and documents, 1969-1971 (Box 13, Folder 70)
      - South Africa Sugar Quota - National Council of Churches and United Presbyterian Church Southern Africa Task Force documents, 1969-1971 (Box 13, Folder 71)
      - South Africa Sugar Quota: Congressional documents, 1969-1971 (Box 13, Folder 72)
      - South Africa Sugar Quota: Background material, 1966-1971 (Box 13, Folder 73)
    - 1972
      - South Africa Sugar Quota (Box 13, Folder 74)
    - 1973
      - Sanctions against Rhodesian chrome / Byrd Amendment (Box 13, Folder 75)
      - Incl. re. Sahelian drought and Tunney Amendment (Box 13, Folder 76)
    - 1974
      - Sanctions against Rhodesian chrome (Box 13, Folder 77)
      - South Africa Sugar Quota: WOA documents and correspondence (Box 14, Folder 78)
      - South Africa Sugar Quota: WOA lobbying lists, notes (Box 14, Folder 79)
      - South Africa Sugar Quota: Congressional documents (Box 14, Folder 80)
      - South Africa Sugar Quota: Background material (Box 14, Folder 81)
      - South Africa Sugar Quota: Other church-related efforts (Box 14, Folder 82)
      - Misc. (Box 14, Folder 83)
    - 1975
      - Angola hearings; Lockwood statement (Box 14, Folder 84)
      - Congressional Black Caucus (Box 14, Folder 85)
      - Misc. incl. re. Rhodesia sanctions, Export-Import Bank Eximbank) loans to South Africa, government appointments (Box 14, Folder 86)
    - 1976
      - Export-Import Bank policy (Box 14, Folder 87)
      - Tunney Amendment / Angola (Box 14, Folder 88)
      - Congressional Black Caucus (Box 14, Folder 89)
      - Misc. incl. re. Henry Kissinger shuttle diplomacy, Stephen Solarz trip to Africa, Namibia resolution (Box 14, Folder 90)
    - 1977
      - Export-Import Bank: WOA notes, statements, correspondence (Box 14, Folder 91)
      - Export-Import Bank: Background material (Box 14, Folder 92)
      - Export-Import Bank: Congressional documents (Box 14, Folder 93)
      - Congressional Black Caucus (Box 14, Folder 94)
      - Misc. incl. re. Namibia resolution, Rhodesia sanctions, South Africa arms embargo, Foreign aid, Congressman Larry McDonald's accusations re. WCC and WOA (Box 14, Folder 95)
    - 1978
      - Export-Import Bank: WOA publicity and press releases (Box 15, Folder 96)
      - Export-Import Bank: Lockwood testimony before Congressional Subcommittee (Box 15, Folder 97)
      - Export-Import Bank: WOA correspondence (Box 15, Folder 98)
      - Export-Import Bank: WOA notes, lobbying lists (Box 15, Folder 99)
      - Export-Import Bank: WOA petition - "A Call to the President and Congress to End Exim Financing for South Africa" (Box 15, Folder 100)
      - Export-Import Bank: Corres., lobbying material of other organizations (Box 15, Folder 101)
      - Export-Import Bank: Background material (Box 15, Folder 102)
      - Export-Import Bank: Congressional documents (Box 15, Folder 103)
      - Misc. incl. re. S.A. arms embargo, Rhodesia sanctions, Stephen Solarz (Box 15, Folder 104)
    - 1979
      - Misc. incl. re. sanctions against Rhodesia (Box 15, Folder 105)
    - 1980
      - Re. Congressional delegations to Africa (Box 15, Folder 106)
      - Lloyd Amendment / re. arms export (Box 15, Folder 107)
      - Misc. incl. re. foreign aid to Mozambique and Namibia, Stephen Solarz, covert aid to Angola (Box 15, Folder 108)
    - 1981
      - Clark Amendment / re. U.S. intervention in Angola: WOA statements, correspondence, notes (Box 15, Folder 109)
      - Clark Amendment / re. U.S. intervention in Angola: Background material (Box 15, Folder 110)
      - Clark Amendment/ re. U.S. intervention in Angola: Congressional documents (Box 15, Folder 111)
      - Human Rights in Africa (Box 15, Folder 112)
      - Namibia (Box 15, Folder 113)
      - Re. Senator Nancy Kassebaum, Chairperson of Subcommittee on African Affairs (Box 16, Folder 114)
      - Congressional Black Caucus (Box 16, Folder 115)
      - Misc. incl. foreign aid legislation (Box 16, Folder 116)
    - 1982
      - Senate Subcommittee on Security and Terrorism Hearings on ANC and SWAPO (Jeremiah Denton Hearings): WOA statements, correspondence, notes (Box 16, Folder 117)
      - Denton Hearings: Background material; material from other organizations (Box 16, Folder 118)
      - Denton Hearings: Congressional documents (Box 16, Folder 119)
      - International Monetary Fund (IMF) loans to S.A. (Box 16, Folder 120)
      - Congressional Black Caucus (Box 16, Folder 121)
      - Navy Port Calls in S.A. (Box 16, Folder 122)
      - Clark Amendment / Arms export (Box 17, Folder 123)
      - Misc. incl. re. Unification Church funding; Intelligence Identities Protection Act; 1982 elections (Box 17, Folder 124)
    - 1983
      - House Subcommittee on Human Rights and International Organizations, incl. testimony of Jean Sindab (Box 17, Folder 125)
      - House Subcommittee on Africa Hearings, incl. on Namibia, internal political situation in SA (Box 17, Folder 126)
      - Campaign Against US/SA Nuclear Collaboration: WOA statements, correspondence, notes (Box 17, Folder 127)
      - Campaign Against US/SA Nuclear Collaboration: Background material (Box 17, Folder 128)
      - International Monetary Fund (IMF) bill: WOA statements, correspondence, notes (Box 17, Folder 129)
      - International Monetary Fund (IMF) bill: Background material (Box 17, Folder 130)
      - Export Administration Act / Solarz, Gray, Berman, Wolpe provisions: WOA statements, correspondence, notes (Box 17, Folder 131)
      - Export Administration Act: Background material (Box 17, Folder 132)
      - Export Administration Act: Non-proliferation amendment (Box 17, Folder 133)
      - Lobbying re. various South Africa-related legislation, incl. National Lobby Day (1983 Jul 19): WOA material (Box 17, Folder 134)
      - Lobbying re. various South Africa-related legislation: Reports of Congressional lobbying visits (Box 18, Folder 135)
      - Lobbying re. various South Africa-related legislation: Material of other organizations (Box 18, Folder 136)
      - Congressional Black Caucus (Box 18, Folder 137)
      - Misc. incl. US contribution to UN Institute for Namibia, Congressional Friends of Human Rights Monitors, Jean Sindab statement to UN Special Committee on Apartheid (Box 18, Folder 138)
    - 1984
      - Export Administration Act: WOA statements, correspondence, notes (Box 18, Folder 139)
      - Export Administration Act: Material from other organizations (Box 18, Folder 140)
      - Congressional briefing on US policy and war in Southern Africa (Box 18, Folder 141)
      - Testimony of Jean Sindab before UN General Assembly and Council for Namibia (Box 18, Folder 142)
      - House Subcommitteess on International Operations / International Security and Scientific Affairs (Box 18, Folder 143)
      - Misc. incl. re. Nelson Mandela Freedom Resolution (Box 18, Folder 144)
    - 1985
      - Anti-Apartheid Act: WOA statements, correspondence (Box 18, Folder 145)